A Guide to the Papers of Virginius Dabney, 1960-1975
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Virginius Dabney 1960-1975
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7690-t
This collection consists of 160 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited on 10 December 1975.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of Virginius Dabney contain extensive correspondence carried on by Dabney as editor of the Richmond Times-Dispatch, in his personal life, and as a Pulitzer Prize- winning author. Other materials deal with his books such as Below the Potomac, The Dry Messiah, and Liberalism in the South, and much useful material collected as research material for these books is present. There is extensive material on the American Society of Newspaper Editors which Dabney served in various capacities including president. A great deal of useful material on race relations, African Americans, the N.A.A.C.P., etc., is present. Recent political history of Virginia is strongly represented in Dabney's correspondence as editor of Virginia's leading newspaper, and in his personal correspondence with figures such as Senator A. Willis Robinson, Francis Pickens Miller, and Senator Carter Glass.
Additional Descriptive Data
Separated Material
Issues of The Bulletin of the American Society of Newspaper Editors(1975 Aug.-Dec.) Removed pending transfer to VCU. 3 November 1977.
Contents List
- Correspondence of Virginius Dabney and Robert H. Meade 1969 April - 1974 April (Box 1)
- The Elizabethan background; also Vikings, Explorers, Privateers ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- The Voyage, 1606 - 1607 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- Flora and Fauna - Virginia, 1607 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- Disease, Famine, Deaths - Jamestown, 1607 - 1610 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous, 1607 - 1610 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- John Smith's Record, Personality and Exploits ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- First General Assembly, 1609; Negroes - Maids from England, 1611 - 1622 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- Massacre, Mortality from Disease, 1611 - 1622 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- Agriculture and Industry, 1611 - 1622 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- Pocahontas - Marriage, England, and death, 1611 - 1622 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- Social and Economic backgrounds of settlers, Indentured servants, 1611 - 1622 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- Negroes - Slaves, 1623 - 1663 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- Great families - Social structure - Customs - Gentlemen - Yeomen - Servants, 1623 - 1663 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- 1644 Massacre - Early Explorers - Education - Miscellaneous, 1623 - 1663 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- Government, franchise, representation, church and state, 1623 - 1663 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- Tobacco - Industrial products, 1623 - 1663 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- Through Bacon's Rebellion, 1664 - 1677 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- Cultural Life, 1678 - 1700 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- Valley and Southwest - Scotch - Irish - Germans, 1701 - 1763 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- Medicine - Ducking Stools - Miscellaneous, 1701 - 1763 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- Slavery and Its Effects, 1701 - 1763 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- "King" Carter and His Class - Social Institutes - Tobacco, 1701 - 1763 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- Religious dissenters - Episcopal Clergy ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- Alexander Spotswood - Golden Horseshoe - Pirates, William Byrd, II, 1701 - 1763 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- Stamp Act, 1st Continental Congress, Virginia Conventions, 1764 - 1783 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- New Virginia Consititution, Entails, Primogeniture, 1764 - 1783 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- Great Figures of the Revolution - Madison, Henry and R. H. Lee ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- Great Figures of the Revolution - Jefferson and Marshall, Monroe and Mason, John Taylor of Caroline, Randolph of Roanoke ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- Great Figures of the Revolution - Washington ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 1)
- Slaves in the Revolution, etc. ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- The Revolution - Military Events, 1764 - 1783 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- Valley and Southwest, 1764 - 1783 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- The Fight for Religious Freedom Education, 1764 - 1783 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- Constitutional Convention of 1788 and miscellaneous, 1784 - 1800 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- Sectionalism - Correspondence, 1829 - 1830, Turnpikes and Canals, 1800 - 1830 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- Embargo, War of 1812, 1800 - 1830 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- Slavery - Colonization Society ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- Education - Dueling, 1800 - 1860 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- Politics and Politicians - Ritchie and Pleasants - Aaron Burr, 1800 - 1830 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- Literary Achievement - Artists, 1830 - 1860 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- Culture, Arts, Heath, Diversion, 1831 - 1860 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- Slavery and miscellaneous, 1831 - 1860 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- The Decline of Virginia, 1831 - 1860 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- Dred Scott, Uncle Tom's Cabin, John Brown, Fort Sumter, Secession ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- Lee's Shoeless, rag-tag troops, West Virginia Breakaway, Dowdey, Chesnut, Blackford, Thomason books, Norfolk in War (Wertenbaker) ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- Jefferson Davis, John M. Daniel, Tredegar, Hospitals, Merrimack, Northern "atrocities" 1861 - 1865 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- Robert E. Lee - Stonewall Jackson Jeb Stuart and other Generals, miscellaneous, salt, iron and coal, railroads, southern women, 1861 - 1865 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- Desertions, Profiteering, Famine, Siege of Petersburg, Fall of Richmond, Appomattox ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- Negroes in the Civil War - First Manassas - Northern and Southern prisons, 1861 - 1865 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- Wells, Mahone, KKK, 1865 - 1870 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- War's devastation, Freedmen's Bureau, 1865 - 1870 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- A. H. Stuart's Committee of Nine, Education, 1865 - 1870 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- Convention 1867 - 1868, Underwood, Hunnicutt, 1865 - 1870 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 2)
- Readjusters, Debt, Suffrage, Industrial DuPont, Miscellaneous, 1865 - 1870 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- Writers, Intersectional Relations, Miscellaneous, 1866 - 1896 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- Public Schools - Higher Education, 1871 - 1885 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- Race Relations, Medicine, Miscellaneous, 1871 - 1883 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- Mahone and Readjusters G. C. Walker, 1871 - 1885 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- Martin, Glass, Daniel, Free Silver, Flood, 1886 - 1900 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- Mahone's final efforts, J. M. Langston - Booker T. Washington, 1886 - 1900 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- Industry and Agriculture, Mckinney Populism - O'Ferrall ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- SWVa. Politics - May Convention (1899) - Tyler, 1900 - 1910 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- Const. Conv. (1901 - 1902), 1900 - 1910 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- Public School movement and Negro angle - Prohibition - Dillard, 1900 - 1925 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- Glasgow - Cabell - Freeman - Mary Johnston - Willa Cather - Tabb, 1900 - 1950 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- Montague, Swanson, Daniel, 1900 - 1925 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- Glass, Jones, Martin Trimble, Davis, 1900 - 1925 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- Social and Economic; Health - Wm. H. Mann, 1900 - 1925 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- Harry F. Byrd, Negro issue, R. R. Moton, World War I, Jamestown Expo., 1911 - 1925 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- Stuart, Slemp, W. Wilson, Woman Suffrage and Education, 1911 - 1925 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- Byrd, Swanson, Glass, Pollard, Slemp, Peery, 1926 - 1942 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- James H. Price, Negroes, Depression and New Deal, County Officers, 1926 - 1942 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- World War II, 1941 - 1945 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- Negroes, Population, Industry, Labor, Nelson Flood, Massive Resistance, Interposition Pollution, 1943 - 1970 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- Holton, Bill Battle, Fred Pollard, Howell, Artists, Writers, Liquor by the Drink, F. P. Miller, 1943 - 1970 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- Darden, Tuck, Norfolk, Parks, Recreation, Howard Smith, Voting Scandals, HFB, Jr., James River, Tourism, Southwest Virginia, 1943 - 1970 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- Battle, Stanley, Almond, City Government, County Mergers, Glass, 1943 - 1970 ca. 1960 - 1970 (Box 3)
- The Writing of History 1965 Oct. - 1968 Nov. & n.d. (Box 3)